So now let's do a short lecture
Giờ hãy có một bài ngắn
on RDS Custom.
về RDS Custom.
So, we know that with RDS we don't have access
Ta biết rằng với RDS ta không truy cập
to any underlying operating system, or customization,
hệ điều hành hay tùy chỉnh bên dưới,
but with RDS Custom we actually do.
nhưng với RDS Custom thì có.
And RDS Custom is for two database types,
RDS Custom dành cho hai loại database,
it's for Oracle and Microsoft SQL Server.
Oracle và Microsoft SQL Server.
In which, thanks to RDS Custom, we have access to the OS,
Nhờ RDS Custom, ta truy cập OS
and database customization.
và tùy chỉnh database.
So with RDS, we still get all the benefits
Với RDS, ta vẫn có lợi ích
of automated setup, operations,
cài đặt và vận hành tự động,
and scaling of the database in AWS.
và scale database trên AWS.
But with the RDS Custom option,
Nhưng với tùy chọn RDS Custom,
the custom part of RDS Custom,
phần 'custom' của RDS Custom,
we actually have access to the underlying database
ta truy cập được database
and operating system.
và hệ điều hành bên dưới.
So we can actually configure internal settings,
Ta có thể cấu hình các thiết lập bên trong,
install patches, enable native features,
cài patch, bật tính năng native,
and we can actually access the underlying EC2 instance
và truy cập EC2 instance bên dưới
behind RDS, using SSH or SSM Session Manager.
của RDS bằng SSH hoặc SSM Session Manager.
So here is my EC2 instance, and as a user,
Đây là EC2 instance của tôi, và với người dùng,
we can now, if it's using Amazon RDS Custom,
nếu dùng Amazon RDS Custom,
apply customizations and SSH into it.
ta có thể tùy chỉnh và SSH vào.
To perform any customization it is recommended
Để tùy chỉnh, khuyên bạn
to deactivate the automation mode,
tắt chế độ automation,
so that RDS does not perform any automation,
để RDS không thực hiện tự động nào,
or maintenance, or scaling, or whatever you want,
bảo trì hay scale trong lúc bạn thao tác,
while you perform your customization.
khi bạn tùy chỉnh.
And also because you may actually break things,
Và vì bạn có thể làm hỏng mọi thứ,
because now you have access to the underlying EC2 instance,
do có quyền truy cập EC2 bên dưới,
it is much better to take a database snapshot,
nên tốt hơn hãy chụp snapshot database,
otherwise you will not be able to recover from your actions.
nếu không bạn khó khôi phục.
So to summarize, RDS versus RDS Custom.
Tóm lại, RDS so với RDS Custom.
RDS will manage your entire database,
RDS quản lý toàn bộ database,
and your operating system.
và hệ điều hành.
Everything is managed by AWS, you don't have to do anything,
Mọi thứ do AWS quản lý, bạn không phải làm gì,
and RDS Custom, it's for Oracle
còn RDS Custom dành cho Oracle
and Microsoft SQL Server only,
và chỉ Microsoft SQL Server,
and you have actually full admin access
và bạn có quyền admin đầy đủ
to the underlying operating system and the database.
với hệ điều hành và database bên dưới.
So that's it for this lecture, I hope you liked it,
Bài học đến đây là hết, hy vọng bạn thích,
and I will see you in the next lecture.
và hẹn gặp bạn ở bài tiếp theo.